# Curriculum Vitæ Jean-Philippe Labbé

Arbeitsgruppe Diskrete Geometrie

Institut für Mathematik, Freie Universität Berlin Arnimallee 2, Berlin, 14195 Deutschland

labbe at math.fu-berlin.de
http://page.mi.fu-berlin.de/labbe

Phone: +49 30 838 75653

#### Area of Specialization

My research is at the intersection of combinatorics, discrete geometry and group theory. My speciality is combining computational, combinatorial, and geometric approaches to study properties of algebraic and topological structures. In particular, my research merges computational experimentations and abstract modelizations to tackle open problems related to Coxeter groups, polytopes (in particular the permutahedra, associahedra and their generalizations), triangulations, and simplicial complexes.

#### MSC2010 keywords:

 $Combinatorial\ aspects\ of\ groups\ and\ algebras,\ Reflection\ and\ Coxeter\ groups\ (05E15,\ 20F55,\ 20B40)$ 

Combinatorial aspects of Stanley-Reisner face rings of simplicial complexes (05E45, 13F55)

Combinatorial and computational aspects of polytopes, Special polytopes (52B05, 52B12, 52B55)

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

10/2016 - 09/2020	<b>Research Fellow</b> , SFB Transregio "Discretization in Geometry and Dynamics" Freie Universität Berlin, Germany
10/2014 - 09/2016	Research Fellow, Israel Science Foundation Grant of Pr Eran Nevo Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Israel
02/2015 - 10/2015	Research Fellow, Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec) Universitad de Cantabria, Santander, Spain
07/2013 - 06/2014	Research Fellow, SFB Transregio "Discretization in Geometry and Dynamics" Freie Universität Berlin, Germany

### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2017 -	University courses
	Master courses: Discrete Mathematics I, Seminar Discrete Mathematics I
	Bachelor courses: Wahrscheinlichkeit & Statistik, Seminar zur Geometrie
2016 -	Programming
	Sagemath: SageDays 79 (Teaching python and Sagemath), Friday Coding Sprints
2008 - 2010	Teaching Assistant
	Algèbre Matricielle, Combinatoire, Algèbre II

## EDUCATION

06/2020	Habilitation, Mathematics / Freie Universität Berlin
10/2010 - 07/2013	Dr. rer. nat., Mathematics / Freie Universität Berlin
	Title: Polyhedral Combinatorics of Coxeter Groups
	Grade: Magna Cum Laude
	Advisor: Prof. Günter M. Ziegler
05/2008 - 08/2010	Maîtrise ès Sciences, Mathématiques / Université du Québec à Montréal
	Title: Approche combinatoire des amas par les éléments triés des groupes
	de Coxeter
	Advisor: Prof. Christophe Hohlweg
09/2005 - 04/2008	Bachelier ès Sciences, Mathématiques / Université Laval, Québec City
09/2007 - 12/2007	Math in Moscow / Independent University of Moscow
09/2006 - 12/2006	Budapest Semesters in Mathematics / Eötvös University

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- 13 published articles in international refereed journals
  - General journals: Canadian Journal of Mathematics, Mathematika
  - Combinatorics: JCTA, EJC, J. Algebraic Combin., SIAM J. Discrete Math., Order
  - Geometry and Dynamics: DCG, Geom. Dedicata, Groups Geom. Dyn., Beitr. Algebra Geom.
  - Computational mathematics: Math. Program., Exp. Math.
- 1 submitted article (Advances in Mathematics)
- 2 preprints
- 3 articles in preparation
- 5 conference proceedings in major international conferences with acceptance rate  $\approx 25\%$
- 1 software package (3500 lines of Sagemath code)
- Sagemath: 55 tickets authored, 105 tickets reviewed,  $\approx (+12\,024 \text{ lines}, -5\,837 \text{ lines})$

#### HONORS, AWARDS AND GRANTS

01/2015 - 12/2016	Postdoctoral Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (70 000\$CAD)
10/2013	Phase II – Certificate of Distinction Berlin Mathematical School
02/2013	Public Prize for Best Talk  Math Slam (Sandwich Theory) – BMS Days February 2013
2011 -	Ambassador, Centre d'étude Collégial, Lac-Mégantic (Québec)
09/2010 - 08/2013	Doctoral Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (60 000\$CAD)
08/2010	Mention d'Honneur – Top Score Thesis Faculté des Sciences, Université du Québec à Montréal
09/2008 - 08/2010	Master Research Fellowship – <b>by Competition</b> Fonds de recherche Nature et Technologies (Québec), (30 000\$CAD)
05/2008 - 08/2008	Summer Research Grant $LaCIM-UQAM, (5~000\$CAD)$
05/2007	Math in Moscow Scholarship – by National Competition  CMS and NSERC Scholarship (Canada), 3 Prizes/Year, (9 000\$CAD)
05/2007 - 08/2007	Summer Research Grant – by Competition NSERC, (6250\$CAD)
05/2006 - 08/2006	Summer Research Grant – by Competition  NSERC, (6250\$CAD)
08/2005 - 04/2006	Tableau d'Honneur – Perfect Grade Point Average (4.3/4.3) Département de Mathématiques et Statistique, Université Laval

#### SELECTED SCIENTIFIC INVITATIONS

## FPSAC International Conferences (acceptance $\approx 20\%$ )

Tel Aviv Israel (Poster, 2020), Daejeon South Korea (Poster, 2015), Chicago USA (Poster, 2014), Nagoya Japan (2 Talks, 2012)

#### Research invitations

Oberwolfach Algorithms in Polyhedral Geometry (Research in Pairs, 04/2019), Institute for Mathematics and its Applications – Minneapolis (Research in Pairs, 04/2018), Oberwolfach Algebraic and geometric Combinatorics (02/2015), Centre International de Rencontres Mathématiques (05/2010)

## <u>Invited Talks</u>

AMS Sectional Meeting Geometric and Topological Combinatorics (11/2019), Institute for Mathematics and its Applications (08/2017), Encuentro Colombiano de Combinatoria (06/2016)

## Combinatorics & Geometry Seminars

Max Planck Institute Leipzig (03/2020), UCLA (11/2019), University of Southern California (11/2019), University of Washington (11/2019), University of Miami (11/2019), Institut Henri-Poincaré (03/2019), LaBRI Bordeaux (11/2017)

## Referee

Annales Henri Lebesgue, Experimental Mathematics, Israel Journal of Mathematics, Journal of Algebra, Algebraic Combinatorics, Discrete & Computational Geometry, New York Journal of Mathematics, Beiträge zur Algebra und Geometrie, Journal of Combinatorial Theory A, European Journal of Combinatorics, Electronic Journal of Combinatorics, Séminaire Lotharingien de Combinatorie, Discrete Mathematics, Australasian Journal of Combinatorics

#### Organizer

- 2 Chair of organization committee (Sage Days 79, 1st BMS Student Conference)
- 5 Member of organization committee (ECCO 2020, 1<sup>st</sup> and 2<sup>nd</sup> BMS–BGSMath Joint Junior Meeting, Sage Days 84, Coxeter Groups meet Convex Geometry 2012)
- 2 Member of organization committee of research seminars at the Freie Universität Berlin (Discrete Geometry group seminar, Polyhedral Combinatorics research seminar)

#### Thesis Advisorship

- 3 completed bachelor theses, 1 on-going
- 3 completed master theses
- 1 on-going doctoral thesis

#### Past and present committees

- Examination: 3 bachelor theses, 1 master thesis, 3 PhD Qualifying Exams, 3 PhD Defenses
- Hiring: 2 post-doctoral positions
- Representation: elected student representative (3), appointed postdoctoral faculty spokesperson (2), board member (Berlin Mathematical School, *Facets of Complexity* Graduate School), Early Career Representative for the Berlin Excellence Strategy University Alliance

#### References

Institut für Mathematik Institute of Mathematics Freie Universität Berlin Hebrew University

Arnimallee 2, D-14195, Berlin Germany Givat Ram, Jerusalem 91904, Israel

#### Victor Reiner Francisco Santos

School of Mathematics Departamento de Matemáticas, Estadística y Computación University of Minnesota Universidad de Cantabria

Minneapolis, MN 55455 (USA) Av. de los Castros 48, E-39005 Santander, Spain

Volkmar Welker

## Matthias Beck

Department of Mathematics Philipps-Universität Marburg

San Francisco State University Fachbereich Mathematik und Informatik

1600 Holloway ave Hans-Meerwein-Strasse
San Francisco, CA 94132 (USA) D-35032 Marburg, Germany

## Interests

## Languages

French: Native speaker English: Fluent German: Fluent Russian: Pushkin State Institute, Moscow Spanish: Upper Intermediate Hebrew: Beginner

McGill University (Advanced 2)

Hungarian: Budapest Semesters (Beginner)

## Cycling

- Constructed three single-speed bikes
- $\blacksquare$  Cyclo-camping: Québec City Îles-de-la-Madeleine (1200km in 7 days)
- Race: Vélothon Berlin 2012 (60km in 1h38min12sec)

## Other

Colonial History of the Americas Ultimate frisbee Sustainable gardening
Theater of the Absurd French poetry Fine Woodworking